A Guide to the Mark M. Jones Papers FA076
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mark M. Jones papers
1890-1965, bulk 1916-1965
1916-1965
Rockefeller Archive Center
Jones, Mark M. (Mark Manderville)
FA076
4.94 Cubic Feet 13 document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for researchd. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Biographical/Historical note
Mark Manderville Jones was born in Cedar Falls, Iowa, in 1890. He started out as an assistant traffic manager, and then manager, for the Waterloo, Cedar Falls and Northern Railway Company. His next job was with the William Galloway Co., also as a traffic manager. He then moved to California, securing a position with the Oakland Chamber of Commerce as Industrial Secretary. In 1916 he married May Irene Rinehart of Akron, Ohio.
Between 1916 and 1921, Jones was Director of Personnel for Thomas A. Edison Industries. When World War I intervened, he served as Director of the Division of Trade Tests for the Committee on Classification of Personnel in the Army.
In 1921, Jones joined the industrial relations firm of Curtis, Fosdick and Belknap as Director of Economic Staff. It was here that he became involved in studies, by the firm, of various economic interests of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. He continued to do occasional work for the Rockefellers after he went into private practice as a consulting economist in 1926.
In addition to Jones' work in economics, public relations, personnel management, and industrial management, he was also President of the Akron Belting Company, 1934 to 1954, and editor of the Executive's Policy Letter, 1948 to 1954. From 1963 to 1969 he was President of the National Economic Council.
Scope and Contents note
The Mark M. Jones Papers consist primarily of studies and reports that relate to various companies and non-profit organizations. Specific types of reports include economic audits, surveys, reorganization proposals, analyses of policy and finances, and development plans. Some writings of Mr. Jones are also included.
Most of the reports were compiled between 1921 and 1935 while Jones was with Curtiss, Fosdick and Belkap, on retainer for that firm, and a private consultant. The following files in this collection relate directly to Rockefeller interests: Boy Scouts of America; Colorado Fuel and Iron Company; Consolidation Coal Company; Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; Grace Dodge Hotel; Institute of Social and Religious Research; Girl Scouts, Inc.; International Committee of the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA); International House; Manhattan Railway Company; National Board of Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA); Palisades Interstate Park; Riverside Church; Rockefeller Center, Inc.; Rockefeller Foundation Retirement Plan; Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) of the City of New York; and Virginia Carolina Chemical Company.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Mark M. Jones donated his papers to The Rockefeller Archive Center in 1985.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 3A 09
Economics; Public relations; Personnel management; Industrial management
- American Baptist Home Mission Society, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Baptist Publication Society, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American Public Health Association, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The American Women's Association, Inc., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Archaeological Projects - List of Interested People, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Art Center, Inc., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Basic English (Payne Fund), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Better Homes in America, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Boy Scouts of America, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Boy Scouts of America, 1925-1932 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Boy Scouts of America (New York City), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Boy Scouts of America, 1936, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Brown University, 1945, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Capitalization of Certain Social, Recreational, and Scientific Projects, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Chamber of Commerce of the United States, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Church Peace Union, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Cité Universitaire, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- City Mission Society Questionnaire, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company
  Related Materials
  See also Box 12.
  - 1919-1924 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 1925 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 1925 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Tentative Improvement Program, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Report on Industrial Relations, 1925; Volume 1 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Report on Industrial Relations, 1925; Volume 2 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Report on Industrial Relations, 1925; Volume 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Bitumous Coal Situation, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Consolidation Coal Company, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Contribution Supported Organizations, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Conventions of Baptist Churches, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Encyclopaedia of Social Sciences, Inc., 1932 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- European Relief Council, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Food Forum Project, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Girl Scouts, Inc., 1921-1928 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Girl Scouts, Inc., 1928 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Girl Scouts, Inc., 1930-1935 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Goethe, Chas. M. - Commemoration, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Gotham Hospital, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Grace Dodge Hotel, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Grace Dodge Hotel - Report, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Henry Street Settlement, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Industrial Extension Institute, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Industrial Relations Assocation of America, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  General note
  Folder missing as of 10/12/2004.
- Industrial Relations Research, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Institute of Social and Religious Research, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Institute of Social and Religious Research, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 47)
- The Interborough Rapid Transit Company, 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 48)
- International Standard Rating System (Box 6, Folder 0048A)
- International House, 1925-1937 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- International House, 1938-1941 (Box 7, Folder 50)
- International House, 1942-1944 (Box 7, Folder 51)
- International House, 1945-1947 (Box 7, Folder 52)
- John Martin's House, Inc., 1930 (Box 7, Folder 53)
- Johnson Immigration Bill, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 54)
- Junior Achievement Inc., 1929 (Box 7, Folder 55)
- League of Nations, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 56)
- Lincoln Memorial University, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 57)
- Reports (Box 7, Folder 58)
  Scope and Contents note
  Long Island College of Medicine, 1932 Maison Internationale, 1935 McKinny Proposal, 1924
- "A Missionary Audit", 1927 (Box 8, Folder 59)
- The Montclair Hotel Situation, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 60)
- National Association of Traveler's Aid Societies, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 61)
- National Social Work Council, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 62)
- The New York Federation of Churches, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 63)
- Reports (Box 8, Folder 64)
  New York Mortgage Conference, 1934 New York Nursery and Child's Hospital, undated
- Northern Baptist Convention, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 65)
- Northern Baptist Convention, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 66)
- Northern Baptist Convention, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 67)
- Northern Baptist Convention, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 68)
- Northern Baptist Convention, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 69)
- "Organization", 1922 (Box 9, Folder 70)
- Pallisades Interstate Park, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 71)
- Reports, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  Periodical for Handwork in the House, 1924 Report on an Office at 81 New Street, New York City, 1924
- Reports (Box 9, Folder 73)
  Phoenix Stone Company, 1925 Physiatric Institute, 1928
- The Riverside Church, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 74)
- Reports (Box 10, Folder 75)
  Rockefeller Foundation - Retirement Plan, 1921 Rockefeller Center, Inc., 1933
- Reports (Box 10, Folder 76)
  "Rorty's Paper", 1930 Save the Redwoods League, 1923
- Reports (Box 10, Folder 77)
  Six International Organizations, 1933 Springfield College, 1956 Sportsmanship Brotherhood, 1926
- Virginia Carolina Chemical Company, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 78)
- "What I Would Do If I Were Foreman", 1918 (Box 10, Folder 79)
- Women's American Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 80)
- Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) - International Committee, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  Folder missing as of 08/11/1992.
- Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) of New York, 1923-1927 (Box 10, Folder 82)
- Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) of New York, 1922-1933 (Box 10, Folder 83)
- Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) - National Board, 1921-1924 (Box 11, Folder 84)
- Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) - National Board, 1924-1930 (Box 11, Folder 85)
- Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) - National Board, 1930s (Box 11, Folder 86)
- Mark Jones' Dossier, 1916 (Box 11, Folder 87)
- Mark Jones' Dossier, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 88)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Accounting Reports, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 89)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Accounting Reports, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 90)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Minnequa Steel Works - Reports (Box 12, Folder 91)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Electrification of the East Mills (Box 12, Folder 92)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - "Production Management Problems" (Box 12, Folder 93)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Coal Lands, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 94)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Various Reports, 1924-1925 (Box 12, Folder 95)
- Colorado Fuel and Iron Company - Publications, 1893-1908 (Box 12, Folder 96)
- Mark M. Jones photographs, 1058
  Jones, Mark M. (Mark Manderville); Jones, Mark M.
  - Portraits (Box 52, Folder 593)